Paolo Morettin

Curriculum Vitae



Expertise: Machine learning, probabilistic models, automated reasoning.

My research lies at the intersection of machine learning and automated reasoning, with a focus on **probabilistic** inference with algebraic and logical constraints. I am currently fully supported by a Marie Skłodowska-Curie Action project aimed at advancing the **trustworthiness of AI** systems by developing verification tools that provide **formal guarantees** on their correctness.

Current position

2022- Assistant professor (RTDa) / MSCA fellow, University of Trento, IT current

Education

 $\textbf{2016-2020} \quad \textbf{PhD}, \ Structured \ Machine \ Learning \ group, \ University \ of \ Trento, \ IT, \ PhD \ cum \ laude$

Thesis: Learning and reasoning in hybrid structured spaces.

Advisor: Prof. Andrea Passerini, co-advisor: Prof. Roberto Sebastiani

2013–2016 MSc in Computer Science, University of Trento, IT, 110/110 cum laude

Thesis: Learning Modulo Theories with latent variables.

Advisor: Prof. Andrea Passerini, co-advisor: Prof. Stefano Teso

2009–2013 BSc in Computer Science, University of Udine, IT, 110/110 cum laude

Thesis: A comparative study on constraint solvers.

Advisor: Prof. Agostino Dovier

Work Experience

Advisor: Prof. Luc De Raedt

2019 Visiting scholar, Statistical Relational AI lab, University of California, Los Angeles, CA, USA

Jul-Oct Tractable WMI models, advisor: Prof. Guy Van den Broeck

2018 Visiting scholar, Declarative Languages and AI group, KU Leuven, Leuven, BE

Apr-Jun Learning hybrid and structured distributions, advisor: Prof. Luc De Raedt

2016 Engineer, Advanced Laboratory on Embedded Systems, (UTRC), Trento, IT

Jun-Nov Formal methods group

2016 Substitute teacher, ITIS J.F. Kennedy, Pordenone, IT

Apr-Jun Substitute teacher in a technical high school (computer science program)

2015 Data science intern, Insight Centre for Data Analytics, University College Dublin, Ireland

Mar-May Dynamic tracking of communities in social networks, advisor: Prof. Padraig Cunningham

2008–2009 **Software developer**, Compix, Pordenone, IT

Consulting, Visual Basic and .NET development

Selected peer-reviewed Publications

2024 Enhancing SMT-based Weighted Model Integration by structure awareness
Gabriele Masina, Giuseppe Spallitta, Paolo Morettin, Andrea Passerini, Roberto Sebastiani

2022	SMT-based weighted model integration with structure awareness Gabriele Masina, Giuseppe Spallitta, Paolo Morettin, Andrea Passerini, Roberto Sebastiani	UAI
2021	Hybrid Probabilistic Inference with Logical and Algebraic Constraints: a Survey Paolo Morettin, Pedro Zuidberg Dos Martires, Samuel Kolb, Andrea Passerini	IJCAI
2020	Probabilistic Inference with Algebraic Constraints: Theoretical Limits and Practical Approximations Zhe Zeng*, Paolo Morettin*, Fanqi Yan*, Antonio Vergari, Guy Van den Broeck	NeurIPS
2020	Efficient Generation of Structured Objects with Constrained Adversarial Networks Luca Di Liello, Pierfrancesco Ardino, Jacopo Gobbi, Paolo Morettin, Stefano Teso, Andrea Passerini	NeurIPS
2020	Scaling up Hybrid Probabilistic Inference with Logical and Arithmetic Constraints via Message Passing Zhe Zeng*, Paolo Morettin*, Fanqi Yan*, Antonio Vergari, Guy Van den Broeck	ICML
2020	Learning Weighted Model Integration distributions Paolo Morettin, Samuel Kolb, Stefano Teso, Andrea Passerini	AAAI
2019	The pywmi Framework and Toolbox for Probabilistic Inference using WMI Samuel Kolb, Paolo Morettin, Pedro Zuidberg Dos Martires, Francesco Sommavilla, Andrea Passerini, Roberto Sebastiani, Luc De Raedt	IJCAI
2019	Advanced SMT techniques for Weighted Model Integration Paolo Morettin, Andrea Passerini, Roberto Sebastiani	AIJ
2017	Efficient Weighted Model Integration via SMT-Based Predicate Abstraction Paolo Morettin, Andrea Passerini, Roberto Sebastiani	IJCAI

Books / Chapters

2023 Semantic Loss Functions for Neuro-Symbolic Structured Prediction
(in Compendium of Neurosymbolic Artificial Intelligence)
Kareem Ahmed, Stefano Teso, Paolo Morettin, Luca Di Liello, Pierfrancesco Ardino,
Jacopo Gobbi, Yitao Liang, Eric Wang, Kai-Wei Chang, Andrea Passerini, Guy Van
den Broeck

2022 Learning and Reasoning in Hybrid Structured Spaces
Book
(Book Series: Frontiers of Artificial Intelligence and Applications)
Paolo Morettin

Service

Program committee / **reviewer** AAAI (2021-2024), AISTATS (2022-2024), ECAI (2020), FMCAD (2023), ICLR (2022-2024), ICML (2021-2024), IJCAI (2020-2023), KR (2024), NeurIPS (2020-2022, 2024).

Editorial board member Journal of Machine Learning Research (since 2023).

Reviewer for journals Machine Learning Journal, Frontiers in AI, Data Mining and Knowledge Discovery, Künstliche Intelligenz.

Other activities

Volounteer AI*IA 2018

Organizer GNI 2016 finals (the Italian Computer Science competition for high-school students)

Languages

English Professional proficiency

Italian Native